say regards his background foreground
mindfulness development
how should one regard the self so as to
experience another
well the first thing is one has to start
seeing oneself as something that's
present there in that experience and
it's because people don't develop
mindfulness according to the principle
of simultaneous presence of the
background in the foreground as in
attention and that which is not attended
but simultaneously there that's why they
usually can't see the sense of self
that's why the self would be described
as an elusive ambiguous thing that you
can never pin pin it down because you
kind of tend your sense of self because
that sense of self it's always in the
background that's why sense of self kind
of merges with it because backgrounds
always there and sense of self it's
seemingly always there so they share
these characteristics and that that
results then in in people just never
seen even even as a phenomena that sense
of self if you start practicing
mindfulness in terms of the discerning
the peripheral phenomena without looking
at them directly
you are discerning domain where that
sense of self does manifest once you get
used to recognizing it for what it is
and stop trying to attend to it directly
and see there's an object of your senses
or something then you get to see that
it's just there a phenomena among other
phenomena and that's when that self
becomes not so not my self you think it
comes yes yeah basically the thing that
self it stays there but what changes
your attitude of ownership of it when
you don't see it you automatically own
it it is yourself when you start seeing
it it ceases to be myself
which means ceases to be the self just
becomes a thing and there is a phenomena
is a background unifying background of
the experience that's it
so by seeing self where it is how this
by learning hard to see the self
learning how to see it cuz you can't if
you look at it you won't see it cuz it's
behind your look that's why this
peripheral mindfulness and vision
results in knowledge you know it that's
the way of seeing it so to speak
internally but you can't see it just by
moving your attention towards it because
it's not object of your senses or your
experience so trying to continuously go
see another is developed by properly
getting to know that sense of self one
will be unable to maintain the notion of
ownership of it and that automatically
is the experience of another when you
see that the background is there to
determine the foreground in as much as
foreground determines the background is
absolutely no room for that self to just
you self as the master creator owner of
the experience
so normally most people we we don't see
this off we don't know the self hmm and
so it's sort of literates expands it
takes over well pretty much yes you have
the father goodies this is whatever
happens it's Mario well did the
assumption of I am I am the center of
all this experience I am the center of
the world basically yeah there is none
to that to proliferation of that
obviously there is an end to that if you
remove the ownership of right things
then you won't be able to maintain that
gratuitous assumption anymore but until
you do you will because it's not a
matter of volition to just stop willing
things to be yours
there are people sometimes the resort to
render you off on the ship having things
as mine is a problem because it feeds my
sense of self so then they start
destroying their own estate property and
throwing every giving everything to
charity and so on thinking they by
getting rid of things you own you can do
a few things so
so getting rid of self-centeredness yeah
which is the ownership of your sense of
self so you don't have to give anything
that well you have to give up sensuality
your well you have to give up a non
purchase behavior but in terms of things
you own as as like items and possessions
theoretically you know to give anything
up if you give up the sense of self then
you can own anything any ownership comes
through the ownership of this sense of
self so so that's why that's the well
that's the problem really so if you want
to give the sense of self up well you
need to see modern senses of it you
can't just give it up theoretically or
wish to give it up because you don't
even know what it is knowing it is
giving it up knowing it nope exactly
exactly exactly once you start
discerning what it is it becomes
apparent that actually has a reason on
its own it's impermanent in that sense
you are not the eternal master creator
of it or controller which means it's
automatically then given up so knowing
the South was you know to know the self
in the background correctly
the self is a sign limit it can be I
mean it's a phenomena limit as a
phenomenon as well but it's this limit
is usually sign in regard to the
established phenomenon so in that sense
yeah for most people the sense of self
appears on the level of the sign they
don't even see it as a phenomena but
obviously they could develop their mind
and start discerning the sense of self
as invidious as it is real as such an
ambiguous general peripheral phenomena
present here and now and then they can
start discerning Namita in regard to
that because Neiman is not a fixed thing
it's a a designation for a position in a
relationship signs and tokens to this
but if you look at them they're gonna
have their own signs and tokens so the
sign that comes that comes from knowing
the self was seen yourself phenomena
well not automatically though if you
were told to look at it like that then
you will see it that's where the
external instruction is necessary
because if petitioner could become very
authentic innocent he sends herself and
seer like a like a relatively dependent
nature but fundamentally he will still
remain assuming the ownership of it but
then if you just pointed it hard to
actually see Eve and that is any other
phenomenon then you will study CERN in
the phenomena or the limiter as in the
science in tokens in regard to that
phenomenon of self as actually not in my
control not mine not pleasurable
dependent thus yeah of course so the
meaning of self
assigns and token you know it that's
what the sign is it's a point in meaning
points it's something a meaning of
something that's what Minnie took up
like a reference relationship so it
would be yeah the sign is always in the
background so by looking at the
background you're gonna start discerning
the signs by discerning the signs you
becoming aware of the background so by
seeing the foreground not going into it
too much attending to particulars too
much well too much in a sense you can
attend to them if you won't compromise
your mindfulness of the experience as a
whole but if attending to the
particulars of the foreground takes your
mind away from the mindfulness of the
experience at home well then you're
compromising it because being able to
see the sign of the
background okay that would be this an
established mindfulness yeah yeah that
would be right mom
sure well there is the there is the
beginning of it if you stick to that
kind of mindfulness you will develop
then the discernment of the sign of even
further which is the sign of your mind
and then the right of you after that as
the Buddha said and then everything else
because it's the middle way because
exactly because of that because you're
neither giving into the senses of them I
know you're mystifying and dismissing
the whole thing going the other
direction you are kind of in between
like with this this is that's it it's
not from me here to there or from there
to me here it's just these two things
arise and cease smooth Aeneas Li
together like nama Rupa vijnana vijnana
nama Rupa that's it that's all that's
there but you're not fully understanding
that you assume yourself in it as the
owner of it so if if one is in that
state but go on ask a question then we
can reformulate if one is doing right
mindfulness balancing in the middle way
they want when when you act
in contact to to unwholesome is the
right effort yeah
because greed aversion delusion is count
as the balance even in slightest amounts
so somebody who is committed discerning
the practice of that balancing as you
said then we'll just see that is
completely incompatible with it so you
can't practice the Dhamma and engage in
greed aversion delusion if you do you
fall from demo for that period of time
whatever you engage you it for however
long you choose to but yeah you can you
can call it balancing in a way think of
it like balancing you can use to it you
balance something for the sake of
balancing and then you within the
balance you start asserting further
opportunity for balance because somebody
who is never ever step back and become
aware of their own situation doing that
first time will feel like wow that's it
this is the experience as a whole but if
you get used to that then you see okay
well now you can actually take the same
principle even further like there is the
subtler more more peripheral backgrounds
to regard to you you fall down and
they're they're more particular
foregrounds with it with their own
limiters and so on it's the same
principle but then you can take it
further infer and how far you take it
well as long as it takes until you're
free from suffering that you measure and
that's when the banner is when that
perfect balance of non green on aversion
non delusion becomes like fully cemented
form of being here and now is that
ruling all the way that's over he he
steadies himself in Habana and the one
who doesn't develop it fully he falls
from the banner as they would ever
described in the suitors it's not like a
great sort of you know I don't know
spiritual wave of energy that sweeps
everything in just its diligence in
repetition and hard work that's why we
will always say whatever was to be
obtained by the manly effort manly
strength manly commitment oh and I'm it
was exactly used
I have obtained he wasn't given to him
by by luck or mystical experience or
something no he's kidding he saw it he
understood it he done it
he developed
we're balanced maybe his conclusion yeah
exactly composure balance kind of again
I mean it's not it's not a wrong term
but it's gonna be misunderstood no doubt
about it but you think about balance
think about composure think about
maintaining the side of the background
while not ignoring foreground or doing
the being engaged attending to
foreground without losing the side of
the background yeah it's a form of
balance that you the more you do the
better you get at it John is the same
same principle establishing your mind
outside of the menu sensuality until
gets studied in it so see that Sheila is
the emulation of that balance you don't
understand it you don't know it but you
start emulating it exactly which can
then give rise to the actual
understanding could you have the set up
in front of you you still not
recognizing it but you're emulating that
that can then eventually bring the
recognition you can't recognize
something if there is if that thing is
not in front of you how can you
recognize it as such and such if it's
not there altogether so the seal and the
virtue of being the prerequisite to any
practice of them it's exactly that
emulating the riderhood emulating the
correct balance the NHANES option on
green on a version on self-centeredness
but yeah that's why Ceylon itself one
result in the Dhamma because you can
emulate only want if you don't make the
effort to understand and succeed in
understanding what you're emulating then
you're not then you haven't developed it
that's why I was like training wheels
so once you've understood
you got the middle way you bet I'm seen
there you don't get a covert you know
exactly because the purpose of the
virtue is now your purpose of the dummer
so the purpose of the training wheels
was to keep you straight and flowing now
you're keeping straight and flowing
without the training wheels as yet
you're gone you are straight up slowly
yes so you've gone beyond I would say in
a way you go beyond deep beyond the
preset sure that's why there were no
precepts in the beginning because the
Buddha would teach the Dhamma and that's
exactly what people would understand
there wouldn't be many misunderstanding
is in wrong views about it so those who
understood it they understood it right
to the core and then they immediately
there was a reference point to anything
that shouldn't be done from that point
of view anything they will be countering
that balance or affecting it but as the
clarity that Bella started waning away
basically it was sort of almost almost to the same
it was sort of almost almost to the same
extent he was the increase in bad
behavior but initially like there were
no rules about I don't know eat eating
like yeah yeah like not eating in the
afternoon or or eating once a day you
know group in the bed at night yeah some
of the rules are risen in response to
like interaction with society that had
nothing to do with AMA or with
obstructing the balance and so on but
those that did arise on account of monks
doing unwholesome things that all came
later because initially he was very
clear what is an obstacle and what isn't
so something is something that isn't an
obstacle can be a rule as well we have
many of the rules that are not actually
obstacles to the Dhamma date kind of
arose in formulating a response to like
as I said interaction with people and
ascites and kings and whatnot but the
ones that they were obstacle yeah
they stayed obstacle they tong if
something is an obstacle to the Dhamma
he does
independent society and the social
context the damaged practicing you
always relate to this universal
principles agree diverging delusion
being obstruction obstruction to that
balance to that composure so that's when
people try to argue I mean I heard
something as silly as that that today
you don't have to be celibate in order
to practice Dharma back in the day they
needed to do that because it was kind of
dependent on the social context and
everything else was just plain
ridiculous if anything today you need to
be twice as hard celibate then back then
because the sensuality is everywhere
completely accessible and the minds are
more proliferating and weaker than back
then because people don't deal much with
hardship today anyway very few do so
they're not naturally tough and so if
anything today you need to toughen up
even more than back back in the day but
if something is a direct obstacle it's
it's a universal obstacle because Dom is
universal so you can't dismiss it
because of a social context or
requirement yeah eating in the afternoon
wearing this type of robes overdoing
that that's all yeah sure it's nothing
to do with the Dhamma is just way of
expression way of relating to the people
but it's not a problem for that very
reason either
or cuts of mindfulness and composure
you're saying about diligence just not
giving in hmm
oh yeah yeah well we spooned out the day
yes yeah exactly
yeah cuz that's the thing you bye-bye by
practicing mindfulness correctly by
being properly composed the issues of
greed aversion delusion become clearer I
think you know exactly the extent of
your responsibility in those things
which means then you know exactly or
gradually you increase the accuracy of
your recognition of what you need to do
if you're not saying no to everything
and everyone all the time because that's
that that's what restraint is all about
it isn't to by the restraining greed
aversion delusion not tolerate greed
aversion delusion not entertain you not
indulging but if it isn't that it's not
your problem so that's that's how you
become aware of exactly what you need to
do your work and by being aware of your
work then you can be diligent in regard
to their work and that's what it means
like doing it whenever it's necessary
like a chore but sure that can arise at
any given time or not arise for quite a
while but when they ever it arises it is done
but when they ever it arises it is done
there is absolutely no like oh I'll do
it a bit later I'll do tomorrow I can
before my meditation and you start 7:00
tonight yeah and you certainly cannot
put a time schedule on it oh and then I
can go back in so forget about it
because I've done my work for today no
sometimes the whole day will be a chore
but in some other days you're gonna have
like weeks
no chores and another hand obviously has
done his duty as the Buddha would say he
finished all his chores he is laid down
the burden of duty yeah he's done he's
done so he doesn't need to do anything
else and that's as a monk that pretty
much the only thing you need to do know
giving the obviously practical
necessities of fetching your robes
walking pin the pad and so on but that
doesn't take your whole day then the
rest of the time that is that should be
the monks priority not tolerating
rigorous delusion clarifying the work in
regard to bleed the vision delusion and
then being diligent in regard to that
so if sometimes you wake up at 2 o'clock
at night and you wake up with the mind
with I don't know affected by hindrance
or something you have to do the work you
can't go back to sleep until you do the
work but in some times if you're sleepy
at 10 o clock in the morning and not as
a hindrance justice Jayant a nurse
because you got up at 2 o clock at night
then you can go to sleep cause it's not
a problem the body doesn't sleep for
something but you don't want to be
tolerating greed aversion delusion so
that's that's where the work is and
ultimately of course for anything sent
like like any sense desire related
sensuality is the chief of the of the of
the desires sensuality sexuality so if
you don't tolerate that you won't be
tolerating anything inferior to that in
other words yet if you free yourself
from sexuality you won't be attached to
any other sensual experience
hence go back to the importance of
syllabus do yourself to see the
importance yeah you gotta know that it's important
yeah you gotta know that it's important
to do that of course of course no that's
my mean by record that's what I'm gonna
say he understands he's understand
sensuality the gratification of it then
the danger in it so you understand the
danger of slacking that particular work
you understand the danger of not doing
that chore so what is the danger any
possible misfortune they can come your
way is a result of you being in the
domain what misfortunes can occur and
you place yourself in their domain by
not this dis disavowing by not saying no
to sensuality as in not freeing yourself
from it like people can say no but they
want it you want to stop wanting it
that's why the restraint is necessary of
course because you come oh I don't want
it but I'm engaging with it in my
behavior no your behavior perpetuates
your wanting of it so you want to stop
the essential behavior you wanna
practice restraint but that in itself is
not gonna fight you need to use that
then to actually discern and recognize
that this is the extent of sensual
pleasure no more no less
this is the extent of it and I do not
want it but until you discern the extent
you can't then decide or rather you
can't then develop your repulsion
towards it because you don't even know
how big it is so you're like you say
notice in short is usually then ends up
being aimed to this particularly in
deputy but overall your mind still finds
the idea that the phenomenon the most
general phenomena of sensuality finds it
pleasing agreeable welcomes it on that
level yeah you might not engage in
anything but body by speech not even a
certain cause thoughts but you still
have the attitude of
well this is this is nice but you
wouldn't call nice something if that
something is dangerous no matter how
nicely coated it is you would say oh
this is dangerous that's why he
understands the gratification in it he
understands the danger and thus he knows
the escape because if you don't
understand the gratification
well you can't understand the danger
because the danger can apply only on
that level the danger rising I don't
want this mindfulness yeah well that's
the only way to slip that's another
thing that will become apparent you
don't slip by not making enough effort
you slip by giving into the opposing
effort that's why all you need to do is
just watch the gate so to speak the
gatekeeper is the Buddha would give
those similes you don't have to chase
everything in or run after everything
that goes up just stay the gate because
you know that's where the problems arise
if they arise the door yeah the sense
doors so if you don't give in to
anything just on their little level no
problems nothing can nothing can
actually right but giving in and then
actually making that effort of giving in
yeah that's how for for mindfulness so
mindfulness becomes effortless when your
mind is a box and Charlotte so as a
reflection you can you can look at
Deception in the foreground and
oh that's that's that's the extent of
sensuality whew
perception in the foreground and feeling
in the background that's I was talking
about in the essay the seating is
feeling feeling and perceiving with
obsession perception that's that's
exactly the point because you are after
pleasure in regard to agreeable
perceptions which is mean which means
the the feeling in the background
motivates you and that's the important
bit here because if you're just looking
at perceptions you'll be avoiding you'll
be denying you'll be trying to get rid
of it but you're not uprooting anything
and in a way that's how you realize the
guy that's how we can discern the
gratification once you restraint you
don't go and try to deny perceptions in
terms of you have a central thought
arises that has happened on its own
that's not your problem the problem is
if you give in to it if you choose to
act out of it well that's that's obvious
problem but then the problem is also if
you if you try to get rid of those
thoughts as well I must stop thinking
something here and people do that very
often because it's actually unpleasant
to have those thoughts enduring about in
your mind because you start to feel it
more the pressure away that the the poor
the pain the dark as the Buddha would
call it but if you don't feel it you'll
never realize the extent of
gratification of it so you shouldn't
definitely not give in by body speech
and mind but you should certainly not
try to get rid of it either
you should be mindful in regard to it
and allow it to endure just so that you
can see the extent of the prospect of
pleasure implied in it when you do then
you see the extent of the danger and
then you can say I don't want it on that
level and then it will work if you say I
don't want it to to particular level
you're not applying that attitude of not
wanting it this is unwanted you're not
applying it on an owner on the level of
the nature of sensuality which is far
more general than the particular
manifestation of it
and that generalities is where you feel
it that's why it's sensual sensuality
motive feeling in regard sensuality motivates
feeling in regard sensuality motivates
motivates your your efforts craving
craving for that pleasure
what about what you know the feeling
when you stop craving in regard to it
you don't know the feeling when you
psychologize or rationalize it then
you're just resorting to your
perceptions again because if you because
your feeling is still not not free from
craving well you don't really know the
perceptions until you know the feeling
and you don't know the feeling I didn't
know the perceptions and you won't be
giving into yeah well cuz they because
you're not giving into perceptions
because of perceptions people give into
perceptions because of the craving and
got the feeling yeah and they'd himself
created that magical connection from
feeling into perceptions this is what I
this is what will satisfy but that's
always on the domain of perception and
feeling always remains on demand of
feeling just recognizing that
independence of each other in itself can
significantly improve the craving from
feeling towards my perceptions krishna
is no point there's no connect it's just
inconceivable not knowing that they are
just completely invisible to each other
so to speak these two domains you keep
assuming this directionality so to speak
of my t said said that's why people are
so sure he can never set this way he
can't because it's applied here and the
problem was over here you want that
because of the problem here I magically
believed that me doing this here
gets rid of that he doesn't you just
distracts you from it so you forgetting
about the problem of craving a negative
feeling you may you develop a belief
which is why sensuality is an assumption
it super Donna
you don't believe that okay that's
that's it that's what this is completely
magical connection between two Terra
cannons we try to manage our perceptions
to get yes sure sure but that's that's
just that is the that is the way it has
to be so even when you start practicing
restraint it's a form of managing your
perceptions but you don't do it for its
own sake you're doing it for the sake of
restraint so that then you can develop
the understanding of it but if you if
you're just doing it for the sake of
doing it just management then that's
always gonna be management can be
restrain your whole life but not
understand anything still better than
being on restrained but it's not the
Dhamma nor the practice of it so do not
understand you think you can interfere
with well you you think you own the
feelings that's you you feel entitled to
- that's what I would say well which
feeling do you own then you see the
pleasant feeling unpleasant no neutral
because if you were truly the owner of
the feeling domain you would only feel
pleasure all the time but the fact is
that they come on their own and go their
own so which one are you the master
allowed intend you not act out of them
and that will automatically result in
mindfulness of them which means being
able to accept that initial pain of not
acting out of feelings wanting more more
of this wanting less of that more of
this pleasure less of that pain wanting
distraction in regard to this oppressing
boredom anxiety all those things have
felt but that's where the main problem is
but that's where the main problem is
routing in regard to this phenomenon
which means you just have to learn how
to endure them and not hide out of them
but allowing it to be because the only
problem is you not being able to help
yourself but assume the ownership of
them so you want to undo that type of
helplessness you want to get to
understand them so that then conceiving
that you're their owner becomes
inconceivable you can't interfere with
any of their grades for that matter even
your intentions which are usually the
closest to the self point of view the
only the only things you can intend are
things that are given as options as
possibilities which means even if we
intend something right here right now
and this immediacy is because it was an
option to do so and those options were
already arisen given on that peripheral
level on their own you can't even think
of you can't think anything from pure
nothingness into being you can't create
that that's not on you things are given
on the peripheral level because of that
there are actual things present as in
the ones that you attend on account of
other things you don't attend to well
exactly you only created a particular
arrangement of things they were all
given beforehand which means you only
you don't create any substance you only
effect arrangement of the given
substance so you are equally on the
level of arrangement not in a substance
your sense itself
but sense of self assumes its ultimate
role did not judge that it effects
arrangement it controls the substance
that's what sense of self assumes it
comes from me there's nothing that you
can create absolutely nothing so that
fundamental point of view anything you
can do what anything that you can do
means it's anything that you can intend
and attend anything you can intend and
attend has had to be given beforehand as
an option to intend it to or attend it
and you see that everything like myriad
of implications as options possibilities
things they kind of bond with the
purpose bound with the context but all
of that comes from the background over
which you actually have no control
that's the direction that you cannot go
under and kind of hold it up as yours
the only way to do so is to ignore it
so put it doesn't this that doesn't
create even even the thing as as most
universal most profound as the dam
itself the Buddha said I didn't create
this no Buddha created this you just
find it like an old path that's been
overgrown in the forest that's it it's
there so one has the understanding of
them having that sure yeah sure it's
while you're composing them in the
balance of the right principle with this
this is that's it that's when it
sometimes they will insist in how's the
Buddha under Oh what's the what happens
what happens for an Ireland what happens
when there is no self and things like
that well you will either just dismissed
questions himself and itself if they're
formulated wrongly or the the most
direct answer he would give to that he'd
be quite indirect he will be the
description of what each don't bother
cuz that's what's left it's that balance
with this this is with ignorance this is
without ignorance this is that's it so
if the experiences without ignorance
that's it that's the our hands balance
like in a way even puta gina is in a
balance as in even puto jana with all
his ignorance can't do anything
different to the nature of the five
aggregates the only thing different
there is is he's a sum he sees
appropriation of it that during the
gratuitous appropriation that's not the
aggregate this is just an attitude in
regard to them completely baseless
attitude that's why he said vijay is
beginningless there is no first point
when he was all on account of this of
egypt came no he's just there but it
shouldn't be there once you understand
it cannot be there that's what it really
disappears what comes to mind the middle way mm-hmm
moderation moderation done these ones
no no because when people act out of the
the view of moderation it's their self
view that decides what's moderate based
on things that they have experienced
which means moderation it's a very
relative thing what's moderate for
somebody won't be moderating for
somebody else and then eventually won't
be moderating for you enough because the
moderation is the only regard to your
previous behavior but if your behavior
was already the behavior moderation then
the new moderation is gonna be even more
moderate and it's exactly what happened
to Giants when they were just going
further and further and further in
saying those things and that's also in
the when Dale's the Buddha well but the
Buddha was the man the man praised the
Buddha and then he asked what do you
think why do you think that all these
disciples have respect for me and the
man said ah because master Gotama
praises eating little and he's little
and he praises eating little he lives
rough he plays a leaving it off and so
on and he said well if they were true
means that I have sometimes I eat a ball
food full to the brim sometimes I have a
second one full to the brim
and I'm disciples that at the same time
would live on our own house rice is just
a handful every two or three days would
get that's it that's all they would eat
if they were to respect me and I kind of
eating little they wouldn't cuz they'd
left in me and then goes on about any
kind of ascetic practice sometimes I
stay in King's palaces while I have
disciples living on the root of tree
they would respect me account that they
wouldn't so why do they respect me
because I talk to suffering and freedom
from it I thought at least some part and
he lists all these different ways at the
jhanas all these different ways of
practice towards understanding and
they're like that's why they respect so
all of that moderation or asceticism if
it's taken further sometimes helpful for
somebody sometimes it isn't but the
criteria is not what I think Apple is
the criteria is that vision
Domenici open up when you said the right
composer the right viewed the right
understanding that's the criteria for
those people which that means they will
know if if increasing asceticism results
in in unwholesome to increase and
wholesome to decrease of course if they
realize okay so I said a system doesn't
work for this set of ugly it's at this
at a time so they they maybe eat more
and and rest a bit more but practice
better that doesn't mean that we're
always gonna stay because they don't
decide it's just a response to wholesome
and unwholesome you don't decide you
don't decide what I'm this type or this
is what works for me know today that
might work for you tomorrow you might
have to go on the root of a tree there's
what I said let those who want to eat
out of like live on the root of tree
Wareham probes and so on do that
let those who don't want not do it that
of course doesn't mean the ones who
doesn't want to do it they'll go back
and live in the city surrounded with
unrestrained people and engages in
surely no of course not just means how
moderate you become how sort of
committed to the idea of moderation
which again two bowls of food once a day
it's not necessarily much it's quite
moderate amount but for somebody who
eats only one handful a day well that's
just pure indulgence if he were to just
look at it from that point of view not
giving into middle really means
basically yeah yeah well no no it
depends living under the tree is extreme
for somebody yeah so middle way means
means not giving into the unwholesome
not indulging it not ignoring it middle
way means dead balance middle and the
balance is wholesome
because it's free from our holes exactly
yeah yeah in a way of course there is
the obvious content of the h3 seeds they
must stop
but any other content yeah I mean people
can wear hemp robes and live on the root
the tree and be extremely misguided and
conceited and vain
I mean like for goodness sake even what
is it devadatta the mom trying to kill
the buddha he was a full-on ascetic I
mean people who are inspired by him when
he went to the Buddha there was actually
the super dimension when he went to the
Buddha and demanded that all these
ascetic practices be made compulsory for
all the monks because it's so
inspirational it's so great and the
Buddha said no don't ask me that you
can't ask the talented and he said let
those who want to do those practices do
those practices now again that doesn't
mean ok so I can live relax in luxurious
life no you have to keep the perspective
on so even the ones who don't do the
ascetic practices are still quite an
ascetic from a lay unrestrained point of
view which means you can't expect to eat
five times a day engage in distractions
just just think about your work projects
and fantasies and whatnot and think of a
Lama you know ascetic renunciate yeah I don't
you know ascetic renunciate yeah I don't
have to live under brutal tree yeah but
you also have you also don't have to
engage with unwholesome either
like somebody can wear silk robes they
not care about it
somebody can wear hemp rose and actually
be quite an awesome about it it doesn't
mean there's no value in trying because
as I said it's not a fixed thing it's
not set in stone
today you might not mind about silk
robes but tomorrow you might start to be
quite attached to it equally tomorrow
today you might mind the hemp robes be
very conceited about it but tomorrow you
might see that conceit and then
abandoned so that's why you can't just
prescribe everybody to do that all the
time because there will be an external
reference point which if people don't
see it's meaningless then you just
emulate things without understanding and
even what you do you're not even aware
that you're just emulating you think oh
so if I do this prescription this method
this set of observance is always without
having to think about anything that's it
that's it it will result in aren't you
but you want it's the recognition of
that balance the mindful composure that
can result in knowledge and vision even
the right ordination in the right image
yeah yeah exactly yeah it's monks
certificate got my certificate your
tradition your Obadiah Acharya so this
like like institution our reputation and
whatnot yeah
well that's that's a lay lay set up if
you have an institution means there's no
like again you can have people
practicing within the institution but
institution itself it's actually a
counterbalance you can't because it's
based on the external projection of
value importance a recognition which
means there's nobody individual
responsibility for it oh it's the
tradition no you choose to do it which
means you could choose to not do it
which means you're gonna feel that then
weight of your choice every single day
but not if you just submit and subscribe
to tradition whatever that tradition
and that does the work for you and
that's why people like that and we met a
few we get very very kind of anxiously
upset and defensive if somebody just not
even dismisses their tradition just
doesn't acknowledge it sufficiently
enough because their whole mode of being
is projected on the external observances
and form how this is what monks are all
about but that's that's an external
reference point that as such cannot
stand for the new place for the tunnel
that's why the dam on the right view is
to be developed and on individually by
those who are wise yeah it's the same
principle that's developed by different
people different sort of owners
different our hands and so on but it
doesn't mean that they will all act the
same like robotic sort of clones or
something the different different
aggregates different individuals what
they all have in common is freedom from
greed aversion delusion but how will
that manifest in their behavior well you
cannot possibly write a prescription for
that in some sort of conformity behavior
as much as visually pleasing is that is
for some people it's like trying to make
everyone wear the same size shorts right
right well okay yes yeah you no way sure
doesn't work yeah no that's why that's
why I like again did you know there's
more than enough rules presets
they've been formed so within that the
only reason if you were going for more
it's because you're sort of misdirecting
your practice because why would you need
more conformity rules for example in the
traditions and like seriously well you
don't you know you don't wear your lower
robe like that that's not our tradition
like you fold it counterclockwise I fold
it with this side before that it's just
like things like that or that's against
our tradition like why would you even
need that kind of observance to the
point of anxious we kind of getting
upset with all the other rules that were
with all the other rules that were
reformed when he himself said nobody
should be forming rules after I pass
away oh you can see all these are no
rules but yeah you see how likely they
were taken then but not so that's what I
mean you recognize that already the
plenty of basis or plenty of rules for
the basis to develop based a virtue and
so on and then you take responsibility
if not you can spend hundred years in
robes and be an equal to two Gina that's
not free from even like the law three
fetters let alone sensuality and
anything else
why cuz you never took responsibility
for the practice he was projected out on
the method on the teacher on the
tradition on the institution whatever
but not on you so
so
when there is ignorance confusion about
the structure
that is something crispy yes yeah you
can say that you know personal minute
and the thing is obviously the notion of
what structure is that's already part of
the confusion is regard to it in other
words the confusion in regard to
structure reality means doctrine means
freeing the structural reality from
craving and greed of illusion delusion
not from laying it all out and figuring
it out because they would require an
external point of view to the structure
which means then it's not a structure if
you can step outside of it
because to super
the track the sign of it check is also
something that's in the back yeah so I
see a person whether it's uber or then a
tsuba it's in regard to what's being
perceived in the foreground through the
six senses satin smell taste touch or
thoughts and it's because that Suba is
in that background which is usually also
a non usual which is where people's
feelings as well ah that's why you kind
of end up assume in the craving for
sensuality the attraction of the
background the pleasant feeling of the
background you end up identifying it
with what you are perceiving so you end
up wanting it aiming at it acting
towards it consuming it and so on so
becoming aware of the the tsuba nimita
means becoming aware of the phenomenon
of beautiful attractive of attraction
and then but then there doesn't that
doesn't mean that that becomes your
foreground or anything like that that's
still in regard to the foreground of the
sensual extends experience but by
discerning the szubin emitter for
example you can then look further in the
further background to it which is they
are super limited that's why every any
any beautiful any attractive it's on the
basis of unattractive it's on the basis
of ugly that's just where it arises in
regard to that which is equally saying
perceived it's the same object you're
looking at but when when attraction is
the nimitta as in the attraction is the
unseen background that's what determines
your attraction towards that object but
if you look beyond that background and
see even further fundamental peripheral
phenomena in regard to that further
periphery of an urn an emitter in
regards to that you then get to not be
attracted to the same thing you're
looking at because you see that it's
actually even more fundamental it's
actually even that beauty that you can
still see kind of halfway now because
but you went further
discern further you
that even that beauty is within the
unattractive it's fundamentally
unattractive if it weren't so you
wouldn't be able to free yourself from
the attraction but attraction is always
second at me but because people never
question it always indulge it or more
often than not they indulge it they give
in to it
you never get to see what's beyond the
attraction you just attraction you're
out chasing the object that you're
attracted to - exactly exactly
once you start seeing the attraction
you're gonna start seeing well you start
seeing the attraction when you stop by
default chasing the objects of your
attraction they will just force you to
be with your attraction which will then
reveal that oh well there is 2cb there
is more to be seen in regard to this
attraction while the same objects are
present in the foreground as a thought
or sight and so on and then you get to
see the unattractive behind it
the pressure of that of attraction like
the unpleasantness of that central pool
you say is passion and then see
the more fundamental yeah yeah yeah
that's that's what mean it's always the
first step first you need to start
seeing the attraction you're not you
start to start seeing the sense of self
yet to start seeing things that you're
supposed to overcome not just in either
or not even looking at direction or
respect to be doing something here and
they'll gonna disappear from over there
so then you realize they cannot be a
tsuba there cannot be
Suba nimita without the foundations of a
szubin emitter in its heart you just
cannot be so any soobin emitter if you
discern long enough you realize ah
whenever there is I you can have a super
that's a tsuba
you can have a super that's less the
tsuba which is how to perceive to be
from the sensuality point of view which
is super then the the Nigam the the sign
of beauty it's basically the sign of
less ability but still pertaining to the
nature of ugly something beautiful and
ugly it's ugly and less ugly disgusting
is stunning less disgusting but equal
disgust yeah a spoonful of excrement is
is less disgusting than a bucketful if
you have to engage with it but it's
actually equally disgusting but people
forget that great that they create a
context of sharing the nature of
disgusting and then oh no this is
actually quite agreeable the less
disgusting becomes becomes desirable
becomes your sensuality but it's less
equally disgusting to the lack in terms
of pertaining to the nature of it just
less disgusting in its content but the
nature is equally disgusting but you can
only see that once first by accepting
the super nimita for what it is and you
can only accept it by stop acting out of
it stop indulging and stop being non
restrained and so on
then when you accept it then you get to
see it and then you can see further then
you can see that there is so there is a
super nimit and a Suman emitter or they
can be super nimita which means that
it's a super limited air as well a tsuba
can be present through Suba and the
tsuba
so then doesn't matter if it's Subaru
Suba a tsuba is there
doesn't matter if it's unattractive
disgusting or a little bit less
unattractive a little bit less
disgusting the disgust is there
the foreground is diversify
yeah the foreground evers yeah the
background is is that it's where the
nature that it's that which determines
the diversity it's a reference point for
diversity a reference point for the
change a reference point for time
lapsing all of that it is pertaining to
the foreground so something needs to
remain unchanged while change occurs so
that you can see that there is a change
if everything is changing all the time
constantly there is no change at all
because you can't tell that everything
is changing because everything is
changing well things can change a
different rate perhaps and then the
thing the change changes at a lesser
rate can become a reference point for
the thing the changes at a quicker rate
but there might be to obstruct for some
people to pend it on but you can you can
you can you can practice that on the
level of feelings and moods like the
general feelings like you can have a
general general feeling present of you
being okay or you being not okay mmm
while their particular more diversified
feelings occurring on a daily basis but
overall you're okay you're meeting and
all sorts of disagreeable feelings on an
individual level voice is annoying this
is disappointing and stuff but none of
that to the point of changing your
general feeling but when when their
general feeling changes any will then
even even the other things that are
you're encountering that are agreeable
will not necessarily make you happy will
bring you back into the good mood so you
could see there like it becomes a mother
currents point the general feeling to
the particular feelings that you have
reference point the determines whether
you're happy or not really whether
you're suffering or not that's when
people are in a good mood and they can
take on the world
cuz nothing can make them suffer because
this mood is there but they fail to see
that that mood has a reason on its own
which mean is such it will have to go on
its own which means then if you
established your whole well-being upon
that mood and then what goes you're
gonna be compromised seriously
compromised well you want to be starting
to discern peripheral in regard to the
peripheral mood that's what I mean it's
the principle solo with a character from
that point of view the new peripheral in
regard to general moods would be that
almost like equanimity would be the sign
of the the nimita in regard to the
general moods because you just see this
feeling comes and goes this feeling
comes and goes this feeling comes and
goes so what would be in common to these
feelings will not coming and going just
sort of being their phenomenon that's
not being felt so like Nibbana is the
ultimate Dhamma
as in the most general fundamental dumb
it's still a Dhamma it's nothing
transcendental in a sense of outside of
this experience it's still a Dhamma but
the Talmud it's free from greed aversion
delusion free from being felt that now
has became pretty much the mode of your
resistance you know the mind has been
developed to such an apex that is just
unshakable from that point of view it's
irreversible the balance the balance the
perfecter balance when he does the
notion of imbalance disappears ting
concealer
they say to you you look at the
phenomenon of things
mmm things things experience where is he
fun most general what is the sign of
that
ultimately speaking yes yeah so you can
build off the mid- nothing one knowing
nothing is sure sure oh you can go in
further you can you can say whatever is
the foe gun well what is whatever
whatever anything that arises to your
attention for your attention
what do all those things have in common
did they are present which means then
the ultimate sign to that his absence
the possibility of absence and there's
nothing other than death the notion of
death which is why the Buddha did say
the one who praised the mindfulness of
death it's like the quickest way Sonny
Bono 8 so it's almost like like dying
without actually dying extinguishing
your being extinguishing your sense of
self extinguishing your lights your your
affections your attractions that's what
people are terrified from even back in
the day when the body was laid out for
them and they would shock panic fall
down on the ground in despair pulling
their hair shouting well if we practice
that that will kill me because that's
exactly what Dhamma is for puto jhana
Dhamma is if they go through the notion
of their own death without dying without
doing anything on account of it that's
what many petitions turn away from it
and jump onto the rich oral traditions
whatever else so they don't take
responsibility coz if they do it becomes
apparent that it's a new and means if
you keep doing it you will die that's
what are you not just said in our
practice Sudama it's like da dying you
should die if you practice on you you
will die before you die it's not just a
poetic expression like you know edge
inspiration the fact that's where people
those people understood what Nibbana it
was that was the thing that when the
Buddha would teach them when the Buddha
would say what he's teaching is they
would understand what he was talking
from navona to be and
with free card that and again it's it's
nothing there's nothing transcendental a
people are not in Habana is because they
don't value the nothingness they don't
value the absence of greed aversion
delusion they don't value the
imperturbable not being felt unshakable
States they don't value that and how do
you know that they don't value well just
have somebody yourself if you have
doubts lock yourself in a room don't
have anything distraction don't do
anything for a whole day just one day
and see how close to the freaking out
you're gonna get with boredom first
board then is gonna turn it to dread an
anxiety and that's exactly that's that
peaceful feeling of Nibbana what
protrusion experience it is a dread and
anxiety not me nor my controller better
distract myself from this but if he were
to prepare himself to not be afraid of
that feeling that's that peace and
that's why it would we say that the
neutral feeling the sublime neutral
feeling the refined neutral feeling is
like it's valued by the wise it's
pleasant when it's known and unpleasant
when it isn't no valuing it
exactly exactly oh they can value it
because they know it huh no this is
actually the true peace so Patricia that
doesn't have peace doesn't have any
Barna no because his eyes are covered by
the metaphysical Veil of Maya and
illusion no it's because he just doesn't
value it
he doesn't recognize it first then he
doesn't value it even if he were to
recognize it even further he's actively
afraid of it he's terrified of it that's
why he's not in Habana just stop being
afraid of your own death for example and
you're already closer to Navarro
because that's where people are afraid
of death now because they know what
death is but because death is just this
vague direction of absence of all of
this that I hold dear that's it you
can't be afraid of death because you
don't you can't even see the death
coming it's always on the direction
external to you so it's from the
opposing direction from where you look
so you being afraid of death it's only
possible because you see a relationship
you see a reference to absence and
denial of everything that you hold there
in your life in other words because
you're attached to life you feel the
absence of life which is what death is
you remove the attachment to life the
the the kind of attitude of holding it
dear and delighting in it why would you
be afraid if the whole thing goes fear
will become inconceivable and that's why
our hand is ultimately beyond death
beyond that fear of that relationship of
absence
because petition I can't even conceive
that when you think that you think in
positive terms again so for many people
just a mere change it's almost on the
level of freaking out as if they would
when they experienced death let alone if
things actually do start going into the
absent mode so to speak losing your
senses and so on but that is the
ultimate limiter and that's that's why
you can use those perceptions to
establish your mind established in mind
from the perception of death
going beyond perception feeling yeah
good good what is the sign absolutely
nothing means and there will be the
ultimate not indicative no appropriate
appropriate in consciousness as in
presence that doesn't appropriate any
presence there will be your experience
as a whole that's like when
consciousness doesn't indicate any
ownership any sense of self nor the meta
finds any footing in that experience
it's just left in scene there will be
the scene in heard just the heard and so
on for all the senses that's it